Nested Structs in Go

Structs can be nested to represent more complex entities:

type car struct {
  brand string
  model string
  doors int
  mileage int
  frontWheel wheel
  backWheel wheel
}

type wheel struct {
  radius int
  material string
}

The fields of a struct can be accessed using the dot . operator.

myCar := car{}
myCar.frontWheel.radius = 5

Assignment

Textio has a bug, we’ve been sending texts that are missing critical bits of information!
 Before we send text messages in Textio, we must check to make sure the required fields have non-zero values.

Notice that the user struct is a nested struct within the messageToSend struct. Both sender and recipient are user struct types.

Complete the canSendMessage function. It should return true only if the sender and recipient fields each contain a name and a number.
 If any of the default zero values are present, return false instead.


Anonymous Structs in Go

An anonymous struct is just like a normal struct, but it is defined without a name and therefore cannot be referenced elsewhere in the code.

To create an anonymous struct, just instantiate the instance immediately using a second pair of brackets after declaring the type:

myCar := struct {
  brand string
  model string
} {
  brand: "Toyota",
  model: "Camry",
}

You can even nest anonymous structs as fields within other structs:

type car struct {
  brand string
  model string
  doors int
  mileage int
  // wheel is a field containing an anonymous struct
  wheel struct {
    radius int
    material string
  }
}

When Should You Use an Anonymous Struct?

In general, prefer named structs. Named structs make it easier to read and understand your code, and they have the nice side-effect of being reusable. I sometimes use anonymous structs when I know I won’t ever need to use a struct again. For example, sometimes I’ll use one to create the shape of some JSON data in HTTP handlers.

If a struct is only meant to be used once, then it makes sense to declare it in such a way that developers down the road won’t be tempted to accidentally use it again.